[music]
Welcome to 2026 release wave two of
business central. This is a la la la la
la la la la la la la la la la la la la
la la la la launch edition video for
what's new in MCP server. My name is
Kenny Pontabidan. I'm a program manager
in the business central team and with me
I'm very proud to have my colleague
Porsch.
>> Everyone my name is Pushad Dvidi. I'm a
senior engineer with the runtime team at
Business Central. Pushart's going to
show some excellent demos in a sec, but
first let's see what we have overall for
you. We're going to talk about two
things. A new tool, actually four new
tools for doing queries and then some
some nice improvements of the user
experience for setting up MCP in
Business Central.
So the query tool in business central if
I should explain it in four sentences it
would be have your MCP host whatever
that is copilot studio vs code or other
have those LLMs construct your queries
then we will compile and run them give
you your data and there's basically no
need to use APIs or anything it just
works like that we have uh introduced
four new system tools
Um, you can see them here in the
configuration. When you enable the data
tool on the server features, you get a
find tables, data find tables tool, you
get a a table relations tool, you get a
table schema tool, and a data query
tool. But it's so boring hearing me
talking about that when we can see a
live demo. So, Purad, why why don't you
show us what you built?
>> All right. Uh
so first of all the main idea with the
data tools was to enable generic data
analysis for our users because with the
APIs of course you have full control
over what APIs you have. You define them
on your configurations and you get the
data according to the APIs that you have
set up. But with the data query tools uh
it completely depends on the permissions
that you already have the tables that
you have access to in business central
and how good your agent is at writing AL
queries. So in my setup, what I have is
I've set up the Business Central uh MCP
as you can see on the left here. And
I've also set up the Microsoft Docs uh
uh MCP, which is great for agents as
well to learn how to write good AL
queries, right? [snorts]
And as an example, I ask my agent a very
simple question. I asked the agent to
get me all my customers, their orders,
and for each order also to get the line
as well as uh just to get an analysis of
what is it that people are actually
buying, right? And as you can see, it
does something. It it takes 30 steps. It
takes 2 minutes. It's a good example of
a longunning agent and it comes up with
a very good analysis, right? It comes up
with a custo summary of what the
customers are buying. The number of
lines for their orders and as you can
see there's also nice observations
towards the bottom that Atlanta
whiteboard accounts for like 46.2% of
open orders. Okay, but let's actually
see how this works by looking at what
the agent did, right? So the agent
starts by searching for the business
central tables and it will provide some
search text and it will get a set of
tables that we have in business central
and then it starts searching in the
documentation essentially searching for
how to write good AL queries and as you
can see here it starts searching for
business central a query object nested
data items and so on. So yeah, so we are
not so just for my understanding so the
MCP host is not sending that user query
to our MCP server and we'll do that
right. Exactly. Yeah, it's a additional
MCP server from Microsoft and you're
free to use it. But at the same time, we
have seen that newer models are actually
pretty good at writing EL query. So they
don't really end up using it as much.
But then as you can see the agent starts
exploring the different tables that we
have in business central and that's what
this uh get business central table
schema is about, right? It will find
tables and then it'll look at what
fields are actually available on all of
these tables.
Once it's done with that, it asks me a
couple of questions like what is the
time period for which I want this
analysis and what are the different
things I want this analysis to cover.
And then finally, it also looked at
table relations essentially
understanding how is one table connected
to other tables in business central
because that's how you write good join
queries in business central right once
it's done with that it starts writing
the AL queries. As you can see here at
the bottom, it will start by compiling
queries. And as you can see, if it
compiles a query and it fails, the
compilation messages you get is directly
from our compiler, right? And so often
times the agent is able to correct
itself and figure out that okay, this is
the mistake I made. This is how I need
to correct myself and then finally it
runs the final queries that it has
compiled and you get the output and
agent is able to access anything. I
think this is a very powerful feature
for generic data analysis from Business
Central.
>> Awesome. Super demo Porchard. Thank you
so much.
>> One a few things maybe that we should
explain here is that since this data is
based on queries
>> that also means that this tool can
basically has the power of queries and
the limitations of queries.
>> Exactly. So whatever you can express in
an AL query is now available to agents.
Exactly. If you have data questions that
will kind of result in a query that is
not supported in the query or even
optimal
>> or or not optimal then of course that
will not work.
>> Exactly.
>> Uh there are also limitations in queries
in business central on how much data can
be returned and for how long the query
can run.
>> Exactly. But I I do think that this is
going to be extremely helpful for ad hoc
analysis uh on where no object
necessarily exists that joins data this
way. All right, the second part of this
video is about what uh the the UX we did
for uh configurations and also a
security feature in case you want to
complete control of whether the MCP
server feature as such should be
available or not. So here is the new UX
for MCP configurations. You can see that
we have added a new box called server
features. Suddenly we're now uh trying
to distinguish between server features s
such as the data tool and the APIs that
are coming below that. And for each of
the d the server features we then have
um the box on the right showing which
tools are uh which tools this particular
feature will open up for. Actually it
will be the combination. So if you
enable a couple of server features
>> uh on the system tools box you would see
all the tools that these server features
enable.
>> Yeah.
>> And then as I mentioned for the security
part we have now a new toggle in uh in
the copilot and agent capabilities page
where you can uh activate or deactivate
the MCP server as such.
And that's it. Pro shot, we just have
one more thing and that is if you want
to learn more about MCP server in
general for Business Central, we have a
landing page for you aka.ms/bcmcp.
And uh with that, that ends our launch
edition video on MCP server. We hope you
will enjoy many of the other videos, but
Porshad and I are out.
>> Thank you.